hello and welcome everyone this is act
INF or stream number 7.1 on March 20th
2024 we're here with Jamie Joyce and
Speaker John Ash we'll have a
presentation then some opening remarks
and a discussion so thank you both for
joining looking forward to this and go
for
it thank you so much and uh we're so
happy to be here my name is j
and you know as stated I'm here with
John Ash who works with us at the
society library and today we're going to
talk about how and why we can make sense
of AI deliberations at the societal
scale using some proven collective
intelligence methods that we've
developed in order to help inform and
hopefully improve decision- making and
you know this methodology is something
that we've taught to students at 32
universities through educational
programming and we've even uh been asked
to extend this type of education to fact
checkers around the world through the
ifcn but besides educational programming
one of the main things the society
library is working on is en enabling
societal scale debate on complex issues
um by creating knowledge graphs now I
think we were asked to speak here today
because of some recent AI generated
deliberation graphs that we've been
releasing on topics related to AI for
example we got an advanced transcript of
the debate between Connor lehy and Beth
Jos and then we create a number of
debate maps about um not not only their
arguments but different arguments that
could be made in the genre of topics
that they were discussing so you can go
to our website to see those if you
like uh I'll show you what it looks like
in actuality very shortly but our work
automating the creation of deliberation
graphs stemmed from our work building
them by hand essentially we've been
building linked knowledge graphs which
map the arguments claims and evidence
from as many detectable points of view
as we can find derive from about 12
different forms of media and this
includes anything from economic impact
assessments to scholly articles to
podcasts and tweets and we model the
back and forth or procon reasoning in
these knowledge graphs um and again we
used to do this by hand and when we did
it by hand analysts would have to spend
thousands of hours combing through
archives and the internet to find
relevant knowledge so that readers
wouldn't have to and of course we don't
just build deliberation graphs we also
enable this complex linked data from our
knowledge graphs uh to be viewable
through more more flattened usable
structures such as micro voting
decision-making models which have been
piloted at the city level and something
we call papers which is an interactive
interface that looks deceptively like a
paper but is unpack across varying
dimensions of argumentation linguistic
register and you can even open sentences
in the paper to see like a Wikipedia
page of information about each and every
sentence which contains a specific claim
but why would we do this well Once Upon
a Time libraries existed because
information was really scarce that's not
why they existed but that's why they
were useful and it was helpful to have
commonly held knowledge that people
could go and collect now we have an
overwhelming amount of information and
it's a fine line to walk to both parse
out re irrelevant or duplicative
information while also ensuring that you
have the maximally context relevant
information to include on a particular
issue essentially it's like really easy
to bias our understanding of an issue by
omission of data so we feel as though
independent public serving institutions
should exist like Library digital
libraries to ensure that people have the
maximal context and the maximum amount
of information available about complex
issues without having to spend the
thousands of hours finding it and
analyzing it themselves so just like the
Library of Congress largely serves as
the intelligence arm of Congress on
policy matters because the intelligence
Community works for the Executive Branch
if I'm not mistaken I think we need to
reimagine what a digital public library
in the 21st century could look like to
serve the public which by default
doesn't give you like a consens view But
A diversity of views and shows you that
when it comes to complex policy matters
there are usually multing multiple
competing points of view with evidence
and argumentation that are indirect
conflict simply a lot of complex issues
have no right answer but must be like
elucidated amongst value trade-offs and
assessment of the evidence that's
available because when we have questions
like how far do you think
personalization of AI assistant like
chat GPT to align with a user's taste
and preferences should go which which
was like a wicked ethical question that
open AI posed over the summer um there
are many competing answers and
philosophies some which deploy
justifications and reasoning to support
why that answer is correct so for
example one response could be that AI
assistant like chat GPT should be
personalized to a user's taste and
preferences to the fullest extent and
highly tailored um based on the user's
past interactions preferences and data
With No Boundaries another position is
AI assistant should understand and adapt
to a user's taste and preferences but
have defined limits on learning
sensitive or potentially harmful
information etc etc so essentially given
the limited powers of observation that
we have and that there's only been so
much investigation into a given question
space it's helpful to see what work has
been done and what reasons and evidence
exist and what preferences people have
which can be informed by the collective
knowledge pool of a given civilization
premodel as a deliberation so that
people can have an easier time logically
processing how information is related
now there's still a gap and we can do
demos uh later on this talk but there's
still a gap between what we've been able
to automate with AI in terms of creating
these large maps of societal scale
deliberation um and what we've been able
to do by hand so here's an example of
one we did by hand um hopefully some of
you remember that there was this great
big debate in the state of California
about the last REM remain nuclear power
plant uh which was called Diablo Canyon
this was a big debate in the past couple
of years um essentially the plant was
slated to be closed down its respective
reactors and 2024 2025 but like the
safety and environmental impact and like
the uh utility of its energy production
has been debated for decades and decades
so we uh essentially deconstructed or
extracted the logical reasoning from
over 5,000 artifacts of multimedia types
in order to create a state scale
representation of what the debate in
California uh looked like what you know
what the debate that people were having
actually look like and we met thousands
of arguments linked based on their
logical relationships across economic
environmental safety political ethical
and other considerations we then fact
checked and steel manned these arguments
as much as possible steel Manning means
to make the argument as strong as
possible through supportive reasoning
and evidence and this took over 8,000
human research hours which is four
full-time human research years um I
could say a lot more about methodology
here but let's just like get the idea of
it and um you can see this map on our
website if you would like
so here's an example of just like one
claim that's enlarged and then the
debate about that one claim so this
enlarging claim reads Market forces and
financial incentives have made the
Diablo Canyon Nuclear Power Plant
redundant non-competitive and
undesirable and that's both like a
highlevel kind of vague but also
substantive claim so as we unpack the
tree we see linked argumentation and
evidence that's more precise uh I know
you can't read it but basically that
high level claim gets broken down into
more specifics like the details of
consumer demand in California across
three Trends and then as you can see
here there's essentially like eight
levels of argumentation back and forth
that's a combination of breaking claims
down into something that can be
meaningfully debatable and then actually
getting down to like the data level of
people arguing over this claim um now
what you're seeing on screen is not
everything that could be unpacked here
it's just one tiny little string that
goes eight layers in depth now I'm going
to show you how many strings exist only
if we unpack three levels deep because
unpacking to the full extent would
actually be too large uh so here we
go so this is just three layers of
argumentation in that same graph it's a
very superficial unpacking these are
again very high level in substantive
arguments which we collected from those
like 5,000 artifacts D duplicated Steel
Man cleaned up contextualized fact
checked linked to references as much as
we possibly could and um you know if we
unpack further we could see those long
like eight layer strings and this is a
2X Speed video that's not on Loop and it
goes on for a minute and 50 seconds I'm
certainly not going to subject you to
watching it but my hope is that you can
appreciate the scale that we're talking
about social media has allowed us to
scale up the nature of communication
since hundreds of thousands or millions
of people can comment on Threads Online
but these threads uh um in this video
are D duplicated in like like high
quality real arguments that were made so
even though social social media scaled
our ability to communicate at the
societal scale no platform we've seen
has really enabled the clean and formal
debate at the societal scale on these
points um social media content is very
useful but you still have to dig through
lots of underdeveloped points so uh this
enormous model of California's debate
was uh created over eight months with
four um full-time analysts and then two
part-time analysts using our tools and
methods largely unautomated by uh llms
which we're working on
today um and hopefully you'll let me
there we go okay great um so again
that's the old process and we're looking
to automate with AI and then actually
point that technology towards debates
about AI itself so when we ask questions
like what should we do about AI we don't
have to spend thousands of research
hours seeing the debate that has already
occurred asymmetrically through
different Publications and platforms on
the web and you know here's the article
on medium if you'd like to read about
our framing of debates about AI but um
there's some problems with how we debate
about AI currently and what I'm trying
to impart today is that you know Twitter
spaces and online polls and citizen
assemblies and books really aren't going
to cut it in order for us to
comprehensively and sincerely model the
collective knowledge and reasoning we
are expressing if our goal is to
sincerely scale conceptualization of
problems and the solution space and then
inquire into truth to try to make
optimal decisions so let's uh dive a
little deeper into the challenges of
mapping AI debates and especially the
problems that people tend to run into in
other projects so of course first is
scope from just a few hackathons that we
were conducting at the internet archive
we were asking hackathon to generate
topics of debate and they came up with
841 unique highlevel preliminary debate
categories across topics like you know
regulation and safety and alignment and
goals and paths and future threats and
risks and on and on so it's actually the
AI debates are enormous debates like
think about that video you just saw and
all the arguments in that Knowledge
Graph scrolling by and how that was just
answers to one question um you know what
should happen to that nuclear power
plant there are potentially hundreds of
questions like there's probably like
millions of questions you could
plausibly ask but if you kind of like
bucket them together um and like regress
backwards there's at least hundreds of
questions that we could uh ask about
artificial intelligence
and uh so if we're to comprehensively
map these AI debates the breadth alone
of just questions we need to answer is
unbelievably immense but before we even
start debating questions we have other
problems like um regarding semantics
when people discuss risk and regulation
it's really important to get straight
about what we mean about AI um you know
there's many terms that people often use
interchangeably with AI the wonderful
thing about government documentation is
that they provide you know in their
regulatory language definitions of what
they mean which is fantastic but not
everyone on the internet does that and
that can prove a challenge and then also
if we're sincerely um interested in
debating and facilitating societal scale
debate it's really critical that we're
sourcing arguments and materials from
different stakeholders and groups who
hold different views um at the society
Library we explore the culture of
different stakeholders in order to try
and understand the different context of
groups that's actually really important
because the context can have a great big
impact on reasoning um which may be
another alleng if groups are left to
themselves to communicate across silos
like here's an example of something that
happened recently on Twitter where um
this was an exchange between AI safety
memes memes and George Hots where um you
know George Hots said it's not the
models they want to align it's you and
then AI safety memes replied with both
and so like in order for that exchange
to happen in Earnest my sense of it is
that there's a great big difference
about what is implied when we talk about
aligning human behaviors where um and I
think that kind of has like U something
to do with like trust and Authority for
people who maybe are more safety aligned
uh adjacent to that idea within their
particular culture there may be this
idea of increasing Harmony and
understanding um uh when they mean AI
alignment and then maybe like other
groups in different communities like
effective accelerationism even though I
don't want to paint any group with a
broad brush of course there may be like
this inherent implied distrust and
Authority so it kind of brings the
question up of like well who decides um
you know so there can be differences
within cultures even though the same
language is used meaning can be implied
and so it's really important to like be
in these communities and trying to
understand to help extricate out all the
implied meaning when people are making
claims um now this is a fun part that I
really like um another challenge of
mapping AI debates is around calibrating
the level of abstraction of the
knowledge that we're surfacing so at the
society Library we create links between
and is not our full ontology this is
very simplified um just so you know um
we create links between highle
sentiments and arguments and more
precise claims and then link those to
the artifacts and the reason why we do
this is because it's faster to read
through all the sentiments than if you
were presented like the full scope of
all those arguments it's much easier to
read like you know 14 positions as
opposed to go through that entire
video's worth of 5,000 linked points um
and then just so we aggregate things up
and allow people to click and unpack um
but what do we mean by a a
sentiment so here's
one um you know fears about super
intelligent AI from the less wrong
Community are just a projection now you
can imagine this being something that
someone would tweet it's like the gist
of an idea and then there are certain
like these kinds of sentiments are the
kinds of things that often pop up in
pulling so like this is an example of
some high level sentiments that were
aggregated in a polus poll about um you
know uh sentiments around AI but if we
were to debate sentiments like this it's
a little bit too high level setting
aside for a moment so like you can't you
know derive is from a and all of that
but um if people do so we're more
descriptive in the way that we represent
deliberation so we accommodate the fact
that people justify value preferences
with uh reasoning and evidence but so if
we were to debate the justifications
around it we would have to break them
down into arguments in each one of the
pieces of reasons that support it so
let's go back to that example Le of the
sentiment that fears about um super
intelligent AI or just a projection from
the less wrong Community now this is
just an example so everyone calm
down um uh and here's an example of an
argument I will read this to you don't
try to read it so uh taking that
sentiment and actually breaking up into
a high level argument here's an example
of extricating out the premises and um
conclusion so premise one members of the
less wrong Community are more likely to
display higher than average intelligence
higher than average intelligence
individuals are more likely to have
experienced more frequent feelings of
loneliness in childhood several studies
suggest frequent feelings of loneliness
in childhood is correlated with
increased likelihood to project that God
is wrathful however according to x
survey most self-reported less wrong
members indicate they do not believe in
God however 83% claimed they were raised
in a household in which one or both
parental Guardians believed in God
though according to Y survey 64% of
self-reported L wrong members indicate
that they have 70% confidence level or
higher that super intelligence would
exhibit wrathful behaviors or or
attitudes uh the powers ascribed to
Super intelligence are often defined in
ways that would make it analogous to
perceive powers of God irrespective of
incentives motivations or perceive forms
of set identities human beings sometimes
project perceptions of one feeling idea
entity or event onto others therefore
less wrong members may have an increased
likelihood of experiencing a cognitive
bias which results from extensive
loneliness due to higher than average
intelligence in childhood which primes
them to transfer projections of a
wrathful god which they are more likely
not to believe in instead onto the the
future behaviors or attitudes of super
intelligence so that's just an example
it's I know it's incom it's not
incomplete and it's like not broken down
to like the greatest extent and that's
because it would just be too much to
read on screen um so but in if we're
going to be meaningfully debating these
things we need to take sentiments build
out argumentation to like steal man them
and then argue over those premises um uh
let's see yeah and like you know each
one of these premises a hypothetical
example has even though some of them are
are
uh claims that are made with actual
references um you know each one of these
is kind of supported by like a stack of
artifacts and so when we think about how
to create a model that shows the debate
the societal scale we're essentially
aggregating up and compressing knowledge
so as to reversible but as an
organization we think it's important to
have an audit Trail down to the
references themselves so readers can
dive up and down the level of
abstraction so it's about maintaining
Providence while enabling accessibility
so it's like we Pro are providing this
Birds I view and then going into
in-depth
detail uh the problem with this though
is that of course we lose detail as we
aggregate up but we've developed an
ontology based on descriptive methods of
how people tend to argue and then how we
can make it concrete to make things
actually debatable so for example you
know people may say things like nuclear
waste is dangerous but it's kind of a
meaningless thing to debate unless you
make it really conrete are we talking
about storing it transporting it licking
it like in what form um and in what ways
is it actually dangerous when you start
breaking it down you can actually get
into something that's meaningfully
debatable but I just really want to
drive home the scale that we're talking
about so I showed you an example of the
difference between a sentiment and an
argument but let's walk through what it
may be like to like actually map this
out so here are the seven claims that
make up that one argument about less
wrong folks that it's not including the
conclusion these are just the oh I guess
the conclusion is there so uh let's just
unpack the the premises because each one
of these premises is debatable so there
may be a set of arguments need to
support why each claim is true this is
why it may look like there's just one
argument for each claim when there could
be like way more and those arguments um
to support the claims in and of
themselves have arguments and like on
and on so hopefully this kind of reminds
you of the knowledge graph video I
showed you ear earlier and hopefully
this helps you appreciate the magnitude
of what it means to not take shortcuts
and really try to comprehensively map
argumentation by breaking it down and
then argu uing over the premises then
arguing over the data that supports
those premises etc etc which we feel um
is how you can in Earnest map societal
scale deliberation especially if we care
about um not necessarily like finding
out the truth because again we have
limited knowledge limited powers of
observation but at least just sincerely
inquiring into what could be
true uh so there's this sort of like
mind-blowing complexity with the volume
and structure of knowledge and we think
we need tools to help us accommodate
that complexity and like I said we work
on many different things like
interactive briefing documents different
visualizations and uh decision-making
models um but you know just getting that
base layer data is like really important
so uh on top is kind of like a layout of
our old methodology and how we used to
build these knowledge graphs by hand and
now we're moving towards automating with
AI by like fine-tuning models at
different layers of our ontological
structure based on our understanding of
like what ontology accommodates
deliberation just generating synthetic
data fine-tuning it um and pairing that
with like claim extraction from the
artifact level and we're working on you
know modeling like the The Logical
relationships of which we accommodate 11
so there's still like a lot of work to
be done but we've made a lot of progress
and I'm happy to open up some of our
toys and we can do some live demos if
you're interested but in general like
this is just the direction that we're
moving in so that you know there can be
this Library institution that exists
where if people want to explore complex
subjects they can ask it a question
press a button and then it goes out and
through a system uh collects the
relevant information logically
structures it so people can see the
different positions and the different
evidence and argumentation that supports
those different
positions and you know we could always
use help we're a 501c3 nonprofit
organization um feel free to reach out
to us to collaborate and you know I'm
really excited to now take your
questions
thanks
awesome thanks for the presentation John
want to give a first remark or any
comments yeah um you know when we talk
about active inference we're often
talking about sort of a generative World
model on which you know we're using to
make
predictions about some underlying True
World um but in the case of you know
language models which
are you know
dominating you know so much of the tech
space right now
and just that the sort of direction that
things are s sort of going is that we're
not actually modeling a real world we're
modeling the artifacts of many separate
different world models and all of those
different world models have a different
uh you know crystallized
representation of that world
and when we train these models we're not
making predictions about a true Ling
World State we're making predictions
about a collective uh representation of
artifacts about the world where there
are many different world
States
and the interface to that to these
models of world
models is sort of evolving
and changing as we grow as people as we
discover what is right and what is wrong
inherently these models are pluralist
because there's so much disagreement
about what the true underlying state of
the world is because it doesn't have
access
to or the language models currently do
not have access
to the real world there is going to be
representations or like a
multi-dimensional represent
that covers all of those different
perspect perspectives and what we're
trying to do is to get like in terms of
the models that exist right now is both
get
a true in some accounting of of the
world but also you know keep the user
talking to the model and different
models have different interfaces on
which they preference right now for
example experimenting with Claude quite
a bit it it tends to really lean into
confirmation bias meaning that
whatever world's model that you might
have that has a tendency
to reflect
and Proclaim or project that you are
right to keep keep you talking if if it
tried to lean into only one
representation of the world it's because
it's not really leaning into the real
world it's leaning into our preferred
representations
of the world basically whether it be
preferencing towards the scientific
worldview whether it is like grock where
you know they literally in their system
prompt say never be woke um whether it's
Gemini which had the debate about their
uh tendency to
um you know when producing like
generated artifacts about historical
periods uh to always include uh
minorities in those
representations there is inherently
going to be baked in some preference to
the world model of the generators so
what we're trying to do here is to to
strip back a that preference or that
bias meaning that we're trying to use as
many models and tools as possible
to
get some form of artifact where you can
holistically
see the largest possible
distribution of actual World models that
are held within that map without
preferencing or biasing any particular
one and give people the capacity to
explore the those differential World
models in that we as a species have
succeeded so much because we are
integrating and
aggregating
um our different perspectives of the
underlying true state of the world
because we have such a limited you know
aperture through which each to see the
world and we have succeeded quite a bit
by summing those differential
perspectives through
conversation and now there's this
evolved sense that we can use these
generative models which are
modeling conversation Space by
predicting you know essentially what the
next token is it can't possibly access
uh
all potential written text ever written
by All Humans but it tries to do the
best that it can
and we're trying to with the full
knowledge that it is sort of a fluid
space create some representations
whereby people can
honestly interact act at a bird's eyee
view of all the potential
representations that might be held
within the model
um so that you can get this
pluralistic God's eye or Bird's eyee
view
of belief space about the true the
supposed true underlying world that
exists those are my
thoughts lot of ways to go I mean just
to connect to the concept of affordances
and policy selection in active
inference a really important thing
that's not shown on those branching
trees is like the probability of each of
those paths so it can be a pure
collection effort like collecting the
Flora and Fauna of a region at a first
pass and then that provides all of these
tools some of which are quite hard to
get to they're like a well-crafted
design or uh thought that might not be
immediately apparent in its um
relationship to apparent claim and then
giving the
toolbox without even necessarily saying
here's what 80% or 99.9% of people in
this or that space feel so instead of
going the statistical route of averaging
out over word use which is already going
to be an issue because it's like the
fuzzy and the statistical as well as the
the dead and the linearized as opposed
to the actual cognitive or generative
model that's making those
words this is providing a tool
bench for at least seeing like you said
from a bird's eye view like these are
the lanes in the highway or these are
the this is the street
map but how you use a street map is
going to be all about where you want to
go all
[Music]
that did you just talk a little about
how we
are attempting to Crow Source in through
the the voting mechanism
yeah yeah so like you know our interest
in the work that uh the work that we're
doing is acknowledging that um a lot of
the work that we could be doing could be
a middle layer for different tools so
like if I'm not mistaken like you know
in tetlock techlock tetlock's literature
there are some evidence that suggest
that one of the distinguishing
characteristics of a super for
forecaster is like ingesting diverse uh
amounts of information like across the
spectrum of potential belief space and
so like having tools that could make it
so human prediction uh could be
increased in quality or more likely to
predict the correct outcomes is like one
potential mitil lator thing the other
thing that we did that uh John just
mentioned is that when we were releasing
our debate maps about AI that are AI
generated which you can see on our
website or LinkedIn our Twitter people
asked for a voting mechanism so we
enabled the ability to for people to
vote on each and every single node and
then it creates a little mini graph on
top of the node so you can see in terms
of how many people are participating
where um uh you know towards uh
disagreement or agreement how much
people believe that now we normally
don't platform that specific um feature
because it has this inherent biasing
effect uh if people believe that
something is highly believed by others
they may be coerced uh to believe that
that has higher value or something like
that which unless you're doing like a
really rigorous robust representative
sampling of people and then have them
vote on that platform um then yeah it
just it just may be like a majority rule
or like self- selected bias kind of
situation so we've never used that
feature before but people asked for it
but uh in addition you know our next
steps include taking our decision-making
model which is a micro voting um
protocol that actually Aggregates up
people's beliefs once they go through
each and every section of a belief space
uh and connecting that with our
knowledge graph so there's many
different decision-making tools
prediction tools that could be built on
top of this link data it's just enough
of a challenge to create this link data
um and pushing to like the maximalist
context that we're interested in pushing
towards in order to make it possible to
make an evidence-based or more informed
decision yeah and that's interesting
thing is that inherently with these
language models uh you know if you go
before
fine-tuning uh they're inherently going
to put
output World Views that are more common
that are more prevalent whether or not
those reflect the true underlying state
of the world if you if you train a
language model only on information from
the 1500s you're going to get a very
very different uh set of outputs for the
distribution of of beliefs and that's
that that notion of the probability of
the different lines that could be traced
out is something that I find to be sort
of woefully under represented under
represented
in the work that it as it currently
stands and hopefully we'll see more of
an evolution towards embracing outputs
that lean into the uncertainty about the
claims being made by the model and also
hopefully bake into the model uh
you know really at at a parameter level
like assessments of uncertainty and
assessments of confidence that different
people have and sort of an e evolving
time based uh binding
to the changing of that map because if
like like I said if we take the snapshot
today it's going to look different than
it does uh in two years there are
various you know sub movements in AI
that do not that exist now that really
did not
exist uh five years ago and so there
will be a process of evolution
where these maps and the way the
information that is represented in them
will evolve
and people will be able to get a more
nuanced representation of the change uh
over time um but it's one of those
things where it's like we're going from
having to rely on like four years of
full research work from humans just
sitting around Gathering documents on
their own and reading through them
manually to okay well now we can get at
least a snapshot of this particular
moment to hopefully creating a evolving
representation of all of those lanes and
all the probabilities
and sort of like uh you you could
imagine like a ton of overlapping
Overton windows and their motion through
time as these Maps you know evolve
through time as the internal
representation of all these World models
held by this one model or these many
different models in this case uh evolve
as training continues as feedback from
the crowd continues and that actually
may be really um useful through time to
be able to predict certain Trends in
human beliefs so like if we were to go
back in time and like model the
argumentation about interracial marriage
which is like you know a values driven
like conflict uh Laden debate at a
societal scale you know we may see
patterns of argumentation like what
about the children it's unnatural
destroy the fabric of society and then
fast forward through time um you know uh
same-sex marriage is an issue that
people are uh debating about and maybe
we see the same pattern of argumentation
emerge what about the children it's
unnatural destroy the fabric of society
so maybe that's going to make it easier
to predict when polyamorous marriage
seems to inevitably become like a legal
issue that people are going to want to
debate is it the same pattern of
argumentation is there anything that is
actually differentiating that situation
like what would be differentiated in a
debate about like inter species marriage
or something like that we a new argument
about like consent because we cannot
communicate with animals um could
actually make a meaningful difference in
the pattern of argumentation so we're
hoping that over time we can kind of
like accelerate through the kind of
arguments that are more related to
culture and values which could be
actually correlated with like disgust or
like unfamiliarity or fear and like
feelings as opposed to like the reasons
that people may deploy to justify those
things which we could see over time like
it didn't result in what people thought
it may result
in that's another interesting aspect
when we would perhaps compare this to
something like act of inference and that
there
is there is supposedly you know this
underlying True World state which you
know when we had uh yeah yeah
debatable event your you know school
where you hosted it there there was like
a very rich and intense debate about the
nature of truth but then on top of that
there is also
this Mor morality space this that exists
only within here right and the only way
to model that distributed morality space
is just by asking
people their their questions
and inherently baked into like these
Maps inherently baked baked into debates
in the first place is
there's the true aspect of it like
people trying to assess what's true but
there's also this uh much more complex
representation of moral and ethics which
often
can not necessarily reflect something in
the real world but reflect something
deeply felt that is very hard to get
access to very hard to model very very
hard to predict but can dramatically
shift very rapidly like for a long time
uh the interracial marriage question was
very very very fixed it it was like
something like 10% of people thought it
was it was okay and then it just very
rapidly shifted um to to the other
direction and people just very rapidly
began to accept oh that that makes more
more
sense
and it's an interesting onsolve question
trying to model that space yeah well one
thing I would say too is that like it's
the reason why our approach is so
context maximalist so instead of like
trying to get people at a citizen
assembly or to like fill out a poll and
have them like Express their preference
or values and then try to justify that
it's like some some things are so deeply
felt and justified by our feeling of
certainty that it can be uh it's almost
like ineffable it can be really
difficult for people to articulate so
instead like deploying strategies to
like look across different stakeholder
groups look across different forms of
media that different stakeholder groups
are expressing themselves um we can
begin to like kind of Link together some
of the justifications that people put
forth because instead of uh you needing
someone who's participating in a poll to
be able to articulate themselves well
it's like you can look across the wide
span of civilization and its artifacts
to see if someone was able to articulate
something and what's the diversity of
those articulations you know when people
feel nuclear waste is dangerous like
where are the people who are talking
about containment long-term storage
Transportation um you know standards of
containment in the United States versus
Sweden like coming in contact with it
leakages that happen that sort of thing
so like by just like looking deep into
the space you can find some people are
able to articulate more so than others
and particularly in published Works they
tend to be more thought out and more
descriptive than what like a real time
performance of a debate or like
participation in like a deliberative
system or like citizen assembly May
yield in terms of like
reasoning yeah that's interesting oh did
you sorry were you still going Daniel
looked like he wanted to pop in I just
go ahead John if you want okay go John I
was just saying about like there is this
inherent aspect of polling which is the
dominant form of getting the sense or
the pulse of the population that the
phrasing of the polling biases the
responses
and also the fact that you're sort of
boiling down their perspective into just
one way or the other and not leaving the
space for them to just say whatever they
say what is interesting about this
evolving space is that we can take and
just cast a as wide a net as possible
with no presumptions baked into um you
know that sampling like with a large
language model in the first place trying
to get a representation all the internet
yes there may be all these bots in there
and there may be all these you know
people trying to influence what is
online but you're not preferencing or
shaping the debate by any particular
question you're just pulling every
possible thing and then trying to
distill out of it compress out of it a
representation that people can make
sense of the territory that exists and
hopefully as time evolves we'll get
clearer and clearer representations of
those
um of the territory with better and
better maps and I just want to pull on
this thread a little bit because this is
actually a really important distinction
within the society Library methodology
and our ontology like when we built
debate maps by hand the question would
actually come last we would just find a
topic and unpack the topics space
through like various techniques we had
like 22 different techniques for how to
unpack a space and look for claims and
what would happen was is we would just
aggregate claims up and what we would
find was when you start clustering them
up hierarchically based on like
reasoning and like levels of abstraction
eventually you would get to what we call
positions which are just general
orientations about something and what
that would do is actually articulate the
question and because like John said the
way you ask a question can be inherently
biasing to a debate like we received an
email and someone said you know how fast
can you make a debate map about like
should AI be governed democratically and
I wrote that back to them I'm like well
we can literally press a button and have
four or five stages of a deliberation
graph done in a couple of minutes but
like you may want to rethink like how
you're asking the question because the
question behind should AI be governed
democratically is should AI be governed
or even beyond that what should we do
about Ai and then we can progressively
formalize to what should we do about AI
well we should govern it how should we
govern it democratically versus all of
these other different governance
mechanisms and like right now we
releasing Maps where we're just asking a
question of our system and pressing a
button just to demo how we're like being
able to automate this but really when it
comes to building the libraries
themselves it's about figuring out what
questions people are actually debating
over most fundamentally because it's
when you find those fundamental
questions that you're casting the widest
possible net of relevant argumentation
it really like creates the scope of
logical relevance and we don't want to
accidentally bias by Omission or
commission and so the best example I can
give for this is our work on climate
change climate change was the first
topic that we began like doing R&D and
our methodology on and what we
ultimately found that of the millions of
questions you could ask about climate
change and like the hundreds of millions
of claims that have been made about
climate change pretty much the debates
about climate change break up into just
six questions um which is like what is
it uh again those debate over terms uh
is it happening what causes it what's
the impact of it what could or should we
do about it and why has this debate
lasted for so along and we found that
when we frame the questions that way
we've never been able to find a claim
that wasn't logically relevant somewhere
in the tree very cleanly across those
six questions and it allows for like a
really clear delineation of like
relevance when it's it may not seem
obvious so like claims about the um
extreme weather events their intensity
and frequency belong under like how do
we know you know is climate change
happening well there's increased
intensity and frequency of Storms and
that's relevant because y y which is
very different than statements about the
intensity and frequeny of uh storms like
killing people and impacting like
underdeveloped Nations which would fall
under impact and you can see how like
maybe it' be very easy on social media
for that argumentation to go differently
where someone's like storms are
increasing in intensity and frequency
some and someone's like yeah and they're
killing people it's like it's it's easy
for um debates to kind of like bleed all
over the place but when you find those
most fundamental questions it gives
clear delineation so you can
meaningfully debate something to
conclusion
because if you don't have that structure
you can just debate infinitely and
recursively forever in all directions um
yeah so that was like a little discovery
that we made early on with our
methodology that led us to believe we
were on the right track in terms of our
approach
awesome well so many pieces here just
some of the terms and the topics that
I'm picking up on that we talk about all
the time in active inference are like
attention the role of affect in
cognition uncertainty including
estimates of One's Own uncertainties
introspection context different forms of
expression epistemic foraging so those
are all really cool topics and then I
got the sense like we're saving or
scaffolding or augmenting the relevance
realization for the cognitive entity
like the ant colony nestmate as they're
going through the street map not trying
simply or only to make an art
artifact which itself has an
understanding like a kind of answer
machine about what should we do about
this power plant in
California it's a totally different
systems design and process and method to
try to develop something that can
address that again begging the question
what does it even mean to address that
question for an artifact when it's the
people who have to do and live with it
um and then just one last piece was like
on some of the the recent active
inference papers touching on these
topics like um designing explainable
artificial intelligence with art with
active inference by Mal abassin and
colleagues talking about how when
uncertainty parameters are explicitly
defined and used as such in these
composable architectures then that
variable in the program like can be
interpreted that way it has that
semantics inter and then that semantics
that are internal can be used externally
whereas this this whole reverse
engineering of Investigation into really
Nano and subm components of statistical
architectures which may come up with
some gold may come up with some Vapor
but it's also kind of like tracing the
connections in brains or ant colonies or
other complex systems which is like okay
you even when you know every
microprocessor it's still is hard to
actually predict what is the effect of a
two lesions at once those are just some
of the challenges of of complex systems
and so it's a really like respect or
even appreciate some of the depth like
many many layers of depth that these
debates are and I think like hold up
that affective component but also
recognize that it's kind of like an
attractor excuse like I'm tired like why
can't I do this I'm tired it is a
totally valid reason and that person
maybe like shouldn't be forced to go to
that event but I'm tired doesn't have
there you could go sub reasons but it's
like it collapses a lot of other reasons
into it and those are our general
sentiments which is why it is hard to
get so precise and follow these
Trails because they take a lot of
attention and craft and suggestions from
others which unless they're curated
you're never going to get exposed to
enough good takes let or takes
period yeah I I super love the um phrase
epistemic foraging I had not previously
heard that and I I love that as an idea
and yeah we we specifically use the
terms arguments claims and evidence to
like kind of preserve claims that people
make like I'm tired it's not all
fact-based like it's a big misconception
people have about the nature of our work
is it's like mostly just facts so I'm
glad you like kind of brought that up
because it's an important for it's
important distinction for people to to
know about our work
too yeah I that's been on my mind this
whole this whole conversation is that
there's sort of like a differing
philosophy
about you know like I was trying to say
something like a model that has a real
has access to the world directly where
it's trying to model the universe trying
to model and predict things that will
actually happen in the real world versus
epistemic Space versus belief space
where it is this AG aggregation of
various belief and we can't come to uh a
a pure
representation of the real world just by
evenly sampling the best thing that we
can do is we can map that belief space
and the distribution of beliefs that
exist within it yeah like to the example
of body temperature which we kind of
commonly return to in active inference
there's a distribution of body
temperatures there's no point in like
denying that it could be outside of a
homeostatic range that excludes people
who need it most basically and so you
can just talk at the like research level
or scale about the distribution then you
could make that into like a weighted
distribution basically a probability
distribution so the area under the curve
sums to one for a given person through
time or for population in a snapshot and
then like that's the beginning
of uh sampling and inferring that from
the thermometer readings or from the
body sensors that's the beginning of
what we can and ought to
do and that's the policy selection
question but that initial sense making
to go from observations um and crashing
them with priors getting to a
probabilistic understanding of of how
things
are then that can be acted upon and it
can be modeled how that gets updated by
taking different
affordances like the different things
that are said in the conversation they
are like selected from kind of a deck of
cards it's like written on the fly as
well but it is selection if you start to
abstract um I'll ask a question from the
live chat um upcycle Club wrote I wonder
what types of information theoretic
patterns emerge from those debate
Maps I wish it was more of a live chat
so I can know what you mean by
information information theoretic
patterns um they can follow up they can
follow up but statistical or
informational patterns in the maps when
you analyze them like as their own data
structures yeah so I mean one thing I
can say that's hopefully relevant to
what the person was querying is that our
onology was built um descriptively and
not prescriptively so before we uh
developed the essentially the strategy
of the society Library we looked at over
100 in 68 different systems and we found
a lot of different systems um were
prescribing a specific ontology to
reasoning and while it's important to
like accommodate more formal forms of
reasoning like actually breaking up
argumentation into premises and
conclusions if we're creating a model
that can inform like you know tools that
could help human reasoning you kind of
have to accommodate how people also
reason so our onology has 11 different
kinds of logical relationships and
there's the typical like Pro cont true
relevant Dimensions to argumentation but
then there's also things like um to be
more specific this means which is a tag
that we put on the edge relationship of
nodes between something vake like
nuclear waste is dangerous and then like
essentially the cluster of more precise
things that kind of have the same
abstract meaning but like are actually
something that's more precise that could
be debated and that can be broken down
you know across several different layers
because people we we couch so much
meaning in terms like if we're talking
about Market forces then we talk about
consumer demand well consumer demand
means very specific things at very
specific times etc etc so in terms of
like information patterns our ontology
kind of like represents that those
information patterns we just notice like
consistently how people tend to reason
and we work to formalize it as much as
possible so it's not just like a
relevant random link data that's kind of
like a visualization of what Twitter is
our goal is to put into formal reasoning
while also accommodating the fact that
when people Express themselves they may
Express themselves more vaguely or they
may have a wider birth of what they
would consider to be relevant which we
then have to um include because it's
such a popular sentiment but then like
also correct with
counterargumentation and so one way we
do that is like we not only have these
Edge relationships between nodes but we
also have tags so things like uh
information in the S like in the model
could be outdated but we include that
information and then just include the
counter relevance argumentation and a
label that says may be outdated because
we understand that people not everyone
has the most upto-date information and
so we're modeling a deliberation we're
going to include what may be like
currently irrelevant given like the
evidence that exists especially if it's
very factual um but uh you know have
that contextualized uh information
attached to it that can only be unpacked
and seen as pairs together so there's
things like that we've done with that
and so I guess one of the information
patterns is that people have a lot of um
unupdated uh in like understanding of a
particular issue um people tend to
Cluster around popular IDE which are
punctuated across different categories
and then people often argue in very
vague ways um I would say another
information pattern is that people get
and again hopefully this is my correct
interpretation of what was implied by
the use of the term um but people tend
to debate about methodology as well so a
lot of like the little strings that we
were debated have to do with like um you
know the changing of models of how we
assess seismic risk throughout the 20th
century and it's like the back and forth
argumentation from like Congressional
hearings and things like that about like
Hey listen as this plant got older and
older we discovered more and more fault
lines but also the model for how we
assess seismic risk changed so it's like
argumentation within Academia and like
activists and like Congress about like
is that appropriate or is that a way of
just like giving a a green like rubber
stamped for the nuclear power plant to
continue and then we we of course find
all of the logical fallacies that play
ad homm and things like that which you
know uh which we have to deconstruct so
it's not ad hominum it's not just like
this is a um you know sorry for the the
knocking there's some construction in
the building um you know people will
make the argument that like a character
who has produced evidence or reasoning
um is like flawed in some way but we
like look for well what are the reasons
that justify that and can we model
debates about
that all very interesting and
like yeah looking at that like growth
and kind of the
occupancy the non-equilibrium stationary
state of where people dwell like these
are the radio stations that people are
dwelling on again there's the spectrum
of all the radios and then here's the
dwelling patterns and so it's like
there's the underlying possibilities of
landscape and then stacking it up and
looking like a sharper and sharper
probability
distribution where people are spending
more of their
attention and than all the ways that the
different computer systems are are in
feedback with that at kind of
unprecedented scale and
type and it's like each one of these
Brit
topics touches upon so many different
Cascades of claims and questions and I
think it was really cool how you talked
about the question
arising from higher
order perhaps very seemingly latent or
oblique aspects of the
space and I guess my question is do the
claims always ramify out like a directed
ayylic graph or how do you deal with it
when there are cycles of justifying
claims yes there's um again finding the
right question is important to um to
kind of create the bounds of logical
relevance so you actually can argue to a
specific conclusion now our tree is what
you saw It's actually an important point
to bring up is um it is it is actually a
graph architecture it's they're not Tre
they they actually do have all these
inter relationships where claims pop up
at different like layers in the map
across different um perspectives and
things like that and that's just like
link data all across and we have
different ways of um detaching how
linked they are so like if there's a
slight difference in context of a claim
popping up in one area and another we
can copy it but like it doesn't update
in the exact same way um even though
like the language and like we
partitioned off like reasoning we've
like broken the link of updating them
because one is only relevant to updating
one section um yeah so there's a lot of
like trickiness with like the modeling
itself and like the updating of this
stuff um but it is kind of U graph-like
and cyclical but the idea of trying to
find what question is going to enable us
to argue to conclusion is so we can just
do that and not just like constantly be
going around and around and around and
around but like you're breaking things
down and you're formalizing it and
you're kind of asking that like Socratic
question of like well how do we know
this is true how do we know this is true
how do we know this is true which tends
not to yield in the same cyclical
patterns that you may see in like other
systems where the ontology is either
really overly restrictive or just like
totally vague and
open and always a tradeoff like whether
working by oneself or in collaborative
or crowdsource settings tag systems are
very general however sometimes they're
just a few letters and so that means
that all the context is being brought to
the table by the tag viewer which ends
up kind of defeating the purpose because
it in some ways doesn't resolve that
semantic ambiguity of what the tag was
about other than just giving the kind of
tological it was used how it was used
whereas with more structured ontological
systems they are sometimes harder to use
or they have a more restricted range
however you can do more powerful
inference with them when the
information's in that format yeah can I
actually show share my screen one more
time I just want to show like this yes
any demos would be definitely cool and
then if anyone has other questions in
live chat go for it and then we'll look
at a demo and look at any last questions
cool all right can you see this
screen um yep okay I'll crop it and
everything okay cool um so this is our
papers interface like you mentioned like
tags and how like um if it's like a
crowd sourcing system like sometimes you
can't like really like extricate out the
meaning of why something was tagged a
certain way so this is the same Diablo
Canyon data except we've rendered it in
an interactive piece of paper where you
can like unpack like the definitions and
things like that but also like you know
here's the highle nine positions that
people take and if you click on a word
like economic you can see a believe it
or not we wrote We rewrote this by hand
this is a more natural language like
kind of article version of all of the
nodes in the graph under the economics
section that support this position so
when we add tags you can actually click
on them and then it has a specific
definition um it's like sometimes we
provide more information within like a
little Wikipedia page for each and every
claim and then you can like unpack um
you know more information argumentation
about that claim space so like the
benefit of like curation is that we can
be as like comprehensive in explaining
and justifying why we're like labeling
and linking things in certain ways um
which again like if if people are like
participating in a crowdsource way like
uh it it's works so people may not be
providing all the information that's
needed in order to um like be able to
interpret what was the original
intention behind linking and
labeling and this makes me wonder
like if we could do it for the oct of
inference literature because people will
say things like marov blankets explain
Consciousness or they don't or active
inference proves free will to be correct
or it proves that it's not correct or it
proves we can't know and some of these
highlevel decisions go into incredible
places and people have incredible
Journeys sharing and working through
some of these and like all of the kind
of Rest
stabilizations In The Meta Learning
Journey and it's like not just does this
method touch upon the scientific
discourse as a source of
stabilizing more natural discussion like
our eggs good or bad for you which is
going to rely on a lot of science but
not even anyone person will ever know we
can also kind of turn the method back to
the scientific
literature because to analyze the claims
made in
papers like either you have the system
you have or you have implicitly that
emulated in your mind somehow yeah or
you don't at which point it's just the
affect that's retained and people will
read something and just think I don't
really like that or I wouldn't have
really said that but of course not
that's because another person said it
and so that is so clear to see once it's
seen yet it is enormously hindering to
understanding and communicating
technical topics like active
inference yeah I mean imagine how many
hours people have to put into like
diving through the conversations that
have already been treaded um just to
like pick up that full context of like
what has already been explored to like
either offer something novel or to
interpret for themselves what where they
want to assign their belief um and so
yeah we we think it's helpful to
Traverse that for people and kind of
create this linked library of ideas like
it's like a Marketplace of ideas so
people can browse and shop and like you
know read the reviews so to speak of
certain beliefs and ideas so that they
can like you know either assign belief
or just like pick up where that
conversation has um you know left off
and like continue it in under you know
some sort of investigation fors over
what is true or what they would like to
believe I wanted to add you know I've
been thinking about this while in this
conversation that the work that we're
doing is not just sort of this top down
from or I don't know how you which way
you refer it top or bottom but from the
question but that there is you know
there's both a top- down and a bottom up
approach where it's like we are trying
to build out a library of artifacts
related to the particular debate space
and then generate them from the claim as
well uh and some of the first work that
we we've been doing is just generating
out from the question using these uh
language models without taking in the
actual space because you know we're in
the wild west I mean like you go back a
few years the only way to pull the
community was through polls and like
there's a lot of bias inherent in those
but as we build out these models we're
also using them
to reach out into specific spaces so
like the process that might occur for
something like active inference is okay
there's something baked into the model
from this overarching view from like
scanning the entire internet but what we
also would do and we're more and more
you know moving towards is pulling in a
library of documents uh that are you
know from experts in the field that are
that is zooming in to a higher level of
resolution and then you
know either training and model
specifically to specific space
or using various techniques that you
know I won't I won't go into quite in
this particular space how how we're
approaching it but there is there is an
aspect of both trying to get the the top
level of the map to bubble out from the
you know this the focused view of
documents that we might pull in as well
as to get it to Bubble from the top
where it's like a very large view like a
combination of two lenses trying to make
it merge in the center towards something
that is as best as POS possible a
representation of belief space in the
moment that the artifact of the map is
generated and viewed by the people
because that's what we want we want it
to reflect the debate as it currently
stands with the full knowledge that it
is
changing yeah very interesting and like
thinking about the epistemic forging
nestmate on the trail all the trail they
cover is is either new to them which is
education or new totally which is
research and Discovery and the process
has to be encouraged to maintain both of
them like at all um question from love
evolve curious how much of society
libraries mapping is openly
accessible yeah I mean we have a ton of
maps that are not online um the Diablo
Canyon map uh is what we would consider
meaningfully complete we still have to
clip a few like um uh strings off of it
because we pretty much stopped when the
grant ran out um you can just go to our
website you can also go to some of our
if you go to our website and go to
libraries you can see uh like in the AI
section for example some of the maps
that we've been releasing which are more
like topical and like related to the
Zeitgeist of what people are debating
which is more of just a demo that we're
making progress in Automation and less
of like a this is a representation of
the debate space um our data is not not
currently open source um but like we're
thinking about it um like the sincere
inquiry into truth is like the
responsibility of like the entire
community and it should be something
that is commonly held um but we're like
a absolutely tiny organization we're
basically like two full-time people and
then like four part-time people SLV
volunteers and we've kind of been that
way for a little while so like managing
open source projects it's like we only
have so much bandwidth if we were to get
like large scale grants we would be
happy to open source like a lot of this
and like do more Community stewardship
in like um you know collectively
building out agentic systems and models
and stuff like that but it's just like
we're our tiny team we're doing our work
we'll get to open source
eventually and you know like I said it's
the wild west things are evolving things
are improving every single day that's
part of the motivation is not wanting
to
make too big of a claim like this is the
perfect representation of the debate
space which it never will be
but right as we're we're evolving as
more and more tools are are coming out
as we can better and better reflect the
human generated map that we did with
Diablo um more and more that you know
will likely be uh you know available to
people but it's a process of taking in
new tools and trying to recreate the
work that is done at that manual scale
and make it automated for everybody yeah
the fast iteration of the work that
we're doing is definitely factored into
into it and then we we have found that
when we demo our tools people get so
excited about them so we were um rolling
out um just like publicly available
tools of like versions of our tools like
we never release these kinds of things
because we're building out different
aspects of the pipeline and like
automating and testing all of that but
even just like one small aspect of the
pipeline like the model that predicts
what the top level positions are likely
to be for a given question which can
help like um direct research goals
people love that so much because they
can ask a question about their life like
people would ask things like what are
the ethics of polyamory or like why
should I give a TED talk or something
like that and it'll just like like make
a prediction about the map of the
spectrum of beliefs and then generate
arguments across varying different
categories so like that's a tool we were
just going to like make available for
people to like play with and use because
every time we demo it people get really
excited and there's other tools like a
little factchecking model that we built
that works pretty well and it's like
we've had a um relationship with the
international factchecking Network in
the past it'd be really great to get
those tools in their hands so like some
things come out at different like times
but yeah it's a lot of bandwidth
limitation on our
end well I guess as we wait for any
final questions in the chat like where
are you going to continue going towards
yeah I mean so um basically our road map
the short-term Road map is that we want
to have a library system where anyone
can ask a question press a button and
then they get these graphs however we
will also be a library where we're
discovering what are these fundamental
questions and building collections for
people in case people don't have like
you know the um expertise to know how
much a question can buas a specific
system this data can then go into
decision-making models like I won't talk
about who we're in conversations with
right now but we've worked um to support
different uh members in government um at
the federal level in terms of creating
legislation and like City level
decision-making so our overall mission
is just to enable more free informed
decisions and that means not only
changing how people make decisions but
also making sure people have sufficient
information and context in order to make
a more free decision like there's a lot
of literature out there about how you
can like bias and like coher decision
making in order to like achieve a
specific outcome like the more
empathetic outcome or like what have you
but we're really interested in like can
we explore the space of enabling
comprehension instead of um
supercharging persuasion and get people
to like have a metacognitive process of
assessing all of their options and then
given an assessment of their options
which is you know can is compressed but
also impeccable um you know have it so
that people make a less biased more
inclusive kind decision which is
products that we've already piloted uh
in government already and so our goal is
in terms of our road map is eventually
linking all the different tools together
the education with the knowledge graph
with the decision making Ms with the
policy um you know if you go on our
website you'll see there's a number of
different programs that are listed under
our program section and so Something
That We're Not shying away from is that
even though we're just and this kind of
goes back to the graphic I showed of
Congress and the Library of Congress
it's like we feel like there needs to be
a Library of Congress that exists for
the public like the Library of Congress
is a premier library and they support
the intelligence and policym of Congress
but it's also available to the public so
we think Library of Congress of the
internet 21st century should exist for
the public but also for decision makers
and that could be think tanks activists
um legislators other like you know more
local decision makers and so getting to
the point where we are informing
decision-making models but also um kind
of seeding the field of um optimal
policymaking is something that we're
interested in because once you have a
sufficient mapping of the problem space
and the solution space and you
understand like what is quote unquote
known in terms of available
argumentation and evidence and also what
is you know quote unquote known about
value conflicts is there way in which we
could seed kind of like a new field of
inquiry where we find Optimal policy so
it's not just majority rule majority
consensus or just evidence-based it's
like what could be optimal based on
people's preferences and the evidence
that exists and like given that my
understanding is there's been some
experimentation to suggest that large
language models can be extremely
creative especially when compared to
humans we may be able to lean on some of
like I know you're shaking your head
it's all debatable um we may be able to
lean especially in the future as these
Technologies um you know perhaps get
better and better and potentially more
creative to find like what is like that
that through line that path forward so
that we can solve or address some of our
most complex challenges without
trampling over people's rights by like a
majority rule or just eliminating
people's preferences by having
evidence-based
only well optimal policy comes up all
the time in act inference and a really
key difference with the active inference
approach for policy selection vers is
like reward reinforcement learning is
like the policy selections based upon a
combination of the pragmatic and
epistemic value that's just one way to
decompose it but the pragmatic value is
the preferences that are being fulfilled
by Future observations like we want to
keep the radiation levels at this level
CO2 at this level temperature pH so
those can be homeostatic preference
distributions that are loose or tight
and then policies that do well in
satisficing that get high pragmatic
value and that's like the traditional
understanding of optimal utility-driven
policy however the other component of
expected free energy is the epistemic
value and so that includes the
Information Gain that's expected about
future observations and like we kind of
alluded to earlier the possibility of
structural change of the underlying
landscape like changes in the
dimensionality of the landscape due to a
technology or like other like nonlinear
changes or distorting changes so even
the most important thing pragmatically
still at least has this like foot in the
door for epistemic value and also have
epistemic humility and together the
epistemic and the pragmatic are part of
the Adaptive policy selection approach
and that can be used to model ant
estmate you know the person broader
organizations and so on yeah excellent
I'm so excited to hear this has been a
topic that has been widely discussed
that's
excellent joh any kind
of closing is thoughts you know I have
my own work with um cognism and you know
I was drawn my attention was drawn to
society library because you know there's
there's a lot of
overlap I would like to just see more
and more in the
future two things that we sort of talked
about in this talk was one the sort of
distribution of certainty about the
world State reflected in all the various
people who this information is being
reflected from and the notion of time a
as the these debates evolve and and
change I think that's that's sort of
essential to
really accurately
represent uh what we're doing here that
you know if you take any particular
language model and try to use it to sus
out uh distributed belief it's pulling
from a large set of text that has no
representation of time unless there
happens to be in each particular text
like some sort of time stamp it's all
boiling it together it's treating
everything as if it happened at the same
time
and that would be a great place to go
into the future is getting a
representation of certainty getting a
representation of the distribution of of
sources with in the data um getting
representation of the evolution of the
debate
and hopefully at some point doing
something like a very very live thing
where it's like rather than having a
polling process where you ask a question
um to a group of people um where you
know they're given a couple of options
it's like okay you have a debate space
in a group of people everybody just
writes whatever they think and then you
take that and you dissolve and compress
it into a map that is pulled from all of
those sources in real time rather than
trying to pull from everything something
that is really really reflective of a
particular an exact data set um that is
like pulled from a group of people who
are given the freedom to say whatever
they want to say in relationship to that
debate and I'll just say that the time
factor is something that we um have
accommodated in our manual creation of
these knowledge graphs so like it's
expressed like in the claim itself or
it's embedded in the metadata of the
claim and then like we also have like
the evolution of things over time
through like timelines of nodes it's a
specific like ontological relationship
is like a sequence of time so like we do
have those kinds of things but like
there's plenty that we need to automate
like there's um the complexity of our
onology is kind of immense and so we're
and so we're just like one model at a
time kind of like building out all these
things to eventually like work in
concert to press a button and then like
structure these things and again what we
determine to be relevant based on
observations of how people argue and
what they care about like trying to
crystallize and formalize by like d
duplicating and steel Manning and that
sort of thing but like recognizing that
you know time series is incredibly
relevant because some things become
outdated when a new piece of information
like defeats its relevance so yeah we've
got a lot of work to do um and so I just
want to like reiterate like um you know
we're a nonprofit We um would love
support you know volunteering is costly
sometimes because it takes a lot of time
to like bring people up to speed you
know when we're an open source project
hopefully we'll have all the
documentation written to be easier but
if you have a way in which you think you
can help us and you're interested in the
project or just appreciate the Mission
please do reach
out awesome thank you Hill
72 see you
bye
e